Guide to the Stanford Alpine Club Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Alpine Club records
circa 1946-2000
SC0611
Rawlings, John, 1950-
5.75 Linear feet (12 boxes)
This collection contains subject files organized by John Rawlings during the research for his book THE STANFORD ALPINE CLUB (Stanford, CA, Stanford University Libraries/CSLI Publications, 1999) as well as original materials contributed by club members. Included are correspondence, photographs, maps, articles, club ephemera, clippings, copy of Rawlings' book, and text, captions, and materials from an exhibit on the Stanford Alpine Club mounted in the Stanford University Libraries. Materials added in 2009 include a copy of the club's booklet "Mountaineering: Freedom of the Quad," 1971, VHS video Dave Harrah "Yerupaja," and a 16mm film roll "Sam & Carol mountain climbing."
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Transferred to Special Collections, 2001 and 2009.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Description of the Collection
This collection contains subject files organized by John Rawlings during the research for his book THE STANFORD ALPINE CLUB (Stanford, CA, Stanford University Libraries/CSLI Publications, 1999) as well as original materials contributed by club members. Included are correspondence, photographs, maps, articles, club ephemera, clippings, copy of Rawlings' book, and text, captions, and materials from an exhibit on the Stanford Alpine Club mounted in the Stanford University Libraries. Materials added in 2009 include a copy of the club's booklet "Mountaineering: Freedom of the Quad," 1971, VHS video Dave Harrah "Yerupaja," and a 16mm film roll "Sam & Carol mountain climbing."
Access Terms
Ames, Lawrence C.; Baxter, Alfred W.; Baxter, Mary Sherrill.; Beardsley, Irene A.; Blankenbecler, Richard, photographer.; Blockley, Marge Barker.; Blum, Arlene, photographer.; Boore, David Meredith.; Boore, Judith Lovelace.; Bostick, Neely H.; Brown, Bolton, 1864-1936.; Brown, Freddy Hubbard.; Clinch, Nicholas, 1930-; Cole, Alex.; Cole, Evelyn.; Collins, James C. (James Charles), 1958-; Crowder, Betsy, 1926-; Crowder, D.F. (Dwight Farnsworth), -1929; D'hondt, Steven.; Davis, Scott.; deSaussure, Ray.; DeStaebler, Hobey.; DeWitt, Hugh E.; Donaldson, Greg.; Frost, Thomas M.; Fuller, Margaret.; Gates, Rupert (Bud); Goad, Maxine Steineke.; Gocking, Roger.; Halpern, Jerry.; Harrah, David.; Hemming, Gary.; Hogan, Jane Noble.; Hopkind, Darien.; Hufbauer, Karl.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Jori, Ellen Searby.; Kendall, Henry photographer.; Kincheloe, Robert, photographer.; Knauth, Felix.; Kroger, Chuck.; Larson, Greg.; Lehman, Sherman.; Little, Meredith Ellis.; MacKay, Ned.; Martin, Bill, photographer.; McConnell, Gloria Kubis Revak.; McCormack, Tom.; Miller, Nancy Bickford.; Moore, Jim.; Ramm-Ericson, Ulf.; Rawlings, John, 1950-; Roberts, Lennie Lamb.; Roberts, Michael.; Simpson, Richard.; Sowles, Dave.; Stanford Alpine Club; Stanford University. Societies, etc.; Stauffer, Karl.; Sturges, Emilie.; Swift, Robert.; Tabor, R. W. (Rowland W.); Van Dyke, Russ; Vennum, Walt.; Vogel, Bea.; Battle Range (British Columbia); Mountaineering expeditions.; Mountaineering--Societies; Photoprints.; Rock climbing--California--History
Collection Contents
- Personal Files, Series 1
  - Lawrence C. Ames (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alfred W. Baxter and Mary Sherrill Baxter (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Irene A. Beardsley (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brown, Bolton (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Marge Barker Blockley (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - David Meredith Boore and Judith Lovelace Boore (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Neely H. Bostick (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Freddy Hubbard Brown (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nicholas B. Clinch (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Alex Cole and Evelyn Cole (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - James C. Collins (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Betsy Swann Crowder (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Betsy Swann Crowder (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dwight Crowder (Box 2, Folder 1.2)
  - Scott Davis (Box 2, Folder 1.3)
  - Ray deSaussure (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hobey DeStaebler (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hugh E. DeWitt (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Steven D'hondt (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ulf--Ramm Ericson (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Margaret Fuller (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Rupert Gates (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Maxine Steineke Goad (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Roger Gocking (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Jerry Halpern (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - David Harrah (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Jane Noble Hogan (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Darien Hopkins (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Karl Hufbauer (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - David Starr Jordan (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ellen Searby Jori (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bob Kincheloe (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Felix Knauth (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Chuck Kroger (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Greg Larson (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sherman Lehman (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Fritz Lippmann (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Meredith Ellis Little (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Gloria Kubis Revak McConnell (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Tom McCormack (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Ned MacKay (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bill Martin (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Nancy Bickford Miller (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jim Moore (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lennie Lamb Roberts (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Michael Roberts (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - R.J. Secor (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Richard Simpson (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Karl Stauffer (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Emilie Sturges (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Rowland Tabor (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Russ Van Dyke (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Walt Vennum (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Bea Vogel (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Subject Files, Series 2
  - Accidents (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Accidents (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Accidents (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - American Alpine Journal -- Club Activities (SAC) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Battle Range, British Columbia, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
  - Bibliography and photocopies of selected articles (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography and photocopies of selected articles (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book -- Comments (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Book -- Finances (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Book -- Permissions (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Book -- Roper's proofread copy (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Book -- Sandstone and Tile (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Buildering (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Buildering--Hoover Tower (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Castle Crags, CA (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Coed Climbers (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Exhibit (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Exhibit -- Harlin and Frost (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Exhibit -- Permissions/Receipts (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Membership Card and Membership Pin (one of each) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Membership List (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1940s-1950s -- Miscellaneous Items (original) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1940s-1950s -- Miscellaneous Items (exhibit reproductions and text) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1960s -- Miscellaneous Items (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Ostrander Hut (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Quad -- SAC sections (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Reunions (incomplete) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Stanford Alpine Club Booklet (1952) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Stanford Daily -- Index and article photocopies concerning SAC, 1946-1982 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
  - Sutter Buttes, CA (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Tetons (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Voluntary Student Organization (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Photographs and Video, Series 3
  - Book pages 1-50 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Book pages 51-100 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Book pages 101- (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Richard Blankenbecler Collection (Tom Frost, Henry Kendall, 1988 Yosemite) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Arlene Blum (photographer) of Irene Beardsley (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Freddy Hubbard Brown Collection (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Scott Davis and Chuck Kroger Collection (Heart Route, El Capitan 1970) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Scott Davis and Chuck Kroger Collection (Yosemite, El Capitan 1969-70) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Hobey DeStaebler (Miraloma Rock 1957, Lost Arrow 1958, Yosemite Point buttress 1959, Clark Range, Shasta, John Harlin, Henry Kendall, Tom Frost) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Hobey DeStaebler (Kings Canyon 1957) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Hobey DeStaebler (Mt. Rainier 1967, climbers John Harlin and Henry Kendall) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Hobey DeStaebler (Battle Range, B.C. 1957, climbers John Harlin, Hemming, and Henry Kendall) (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Hobey DeStaebler (SAC trans--Sierra ski trip 1968: William rope rescue, Mike Roberts, Lennie Lamb) (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Hobey DeStaebler (miscellaneous slides) (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Greg Donaldson Collection (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Ulf Ramm-Ericson, photographer; includes images of Al Baxter, Fritz Lippmann, Rupert "Bud" Gates (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Robert Kincheloe Collection (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bill Martin Collection (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - SAC miscellaneous, 1940s-60s (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - SAC Scrapbook, copies of photographs from (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Robert Swift Collection (Yosemite, Karakorum) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Rowland Tabor Collection (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bea Vogel Collection (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - SAC Trans -- Sierra ski tour 1950 (Rowland Tabor, Jack Weicker, John Mowat, George Mowat) (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, with index prints, 1 optical disc(s) (Box 8.1U)
  - Stanford Alpine Club, "El Cap 5/2", 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Sources and Publication, Series 4
  - Photocopy (bound) of Stanford Alpine Club Journal, 1958 (Box 9)
  - Photocopy (bound) of assorted sources on SAC from the Stanford University Archives (Box 9)
  - Transcripts (bound - 2 v.) of the Stanford Alpine Club oral histories (Box 9)
  - Mock-up of Rawlings' book (Box 9)
  - Copy of published book (The Stanford Alpine Club: featuring the photography of Tom Frost, Henry Kendall and Leigh Ortenburger) (Box 9)
  - Exhibit props, photographs, and magazine articles (Box 10)
  - Photographs, maps, and other items accompanying "Battle Range" subject files (Box 11)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2009-153
  - Dave Harrah "Yerupaja", 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 12)
  - "Sam and Carol mountain climbing", 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 12)
  - Images [CD #1 missing its CD at the time of acquisition by the Archives], 4 optical disc(s) (Box 12)
  - "Mountaineering: Freedom of the Quad", 1971; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Original negatives of photos of Mary Sherrill Baxter and Al and Mary (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Copy negatives of photos of SAC members, events, 1950-86 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Negatives of Quad images, 1951-53 (Box 12, Folder 4)